Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

McGill University - Génome Québec Innovation Centre

I am a statistical modeler and applied machine learning researcher with expertise in probabilistic, Bayesian, and latent variable modeling. Currently, I am a post-doctoral research fellow in computational biology working on the application of Bayesian statistics and machine learning to transcriptomics and epigenomics data. I received a PhD in Quantitative Psychology (statistics applied to modeling psychological and neuroimaging data), a masters degree in Mathematical Statistics, and a masters degree in Psychometrics from the Ohio State University.

Experience

Postdoctoral Research Fellow.	
McGill University-Génome Québec Innovation Centre Research Lab of Dr. Najafabadi, Department of Human Genetics	Montreal, Canada 06/2018-Present
Massachusetts General Hospital-Harvard Medical School Research Lab of Dr. Pinello, Molecular Pathology Unit	Massachusetts, USA 06/2017-05/2018
Research Intern	
Oepartment of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program Research Lab of Dr. Ewy Mathè, The Ohio State University	Ohio, USA 05/2016-08/2016
University Teaching Assistant.	
The Ohio State University Graduate Teaching Associate (Statistics) Served as a Teaching Assistant for three courses: Repeated Measures Model Models, and Data Analysis in Psychology.	Ohio, USA 2013–2017 Is, Covariance Structure
Test Preparation Instructor	
Independent Tutor Teacher of General English, TOEFL, and GMAT	Moscow, Russia 2001-2012

Education

Academic Qualifications.....

PhD in Quantitative Psychology (i.e. Applied Statistics)

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2015-2017

Dissertation Topic: 'Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States'

Master of Science in Statistics

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2012-2015

Master's Degree in Psychometrics

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modeling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

Bachelor's Degree in Psychology

Pennsylvania, USA

The Pennsylvania State University

2011-2012

Publications

Journal Papers (first author/co-author)

- o Baskin, E.[†], Farouni, R.[†], and Mathè, E. (2016). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. *Bioinformatics* doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw688. Preprint available at http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/14/080564.full.pdf+html
- o Pinello, L.[†], Farouni, R.[†], and Yuan, G-C. (2018). Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. *Bioinformatics* https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty031. Preprint available at https://doi.org/10.1101/199067
- o Clement, K.†, Farouni, R.†, Bauer, D. E., and Pinello, L. (2018). Design and analysis of unique molecular identifiers for deep amplicon sequencing. *Bioinformatics* (accepted). Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2018/03/23/288118.full.pdf

Journal Papers (middle author/contributor).....

- Seruggia, D., Oti, M., Tripathi, P., Canver, M.C., Leblanc, L. Giammartino, L., Nefzger, C.M., Yang Sun, Y.B., Farouni, R., Polo, J.M., Pinello, L., Apostolou, E., Kim, J., Orkin, S.H., and Das, P.P. (2018). TAF5L/TAF6L maintains self-renewal of embryonic stem cells via MYC regulatory network. (submitted)
- o Grüning, B., Dale, R., Sjödin, A., Rowe, J., Chapman, B. A., Tomkins-Tinch, C. H., The Bioconda Team, and Köster, J.(2018) Bioconda: A sustainable and comprehensive software distribution for the life sciences. *Nature Methods*. (accepted), Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2017/10/27/207092 (Bioconda team member contributor)

- Hsu, J. Y., Fulco, C.P., Cole, M., Canver, M. C., Pellin D., Sher, F, Farouni, R., Clement K., Biasco L., Engreitz, J. M., Lander, E. S., Joung J. K., Bauer, D. E., Pinello, L. (2018). CRISPR-SURF: Exploratory and interactive software for analyzing CRISPR-based tiling screens.(submitted). Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/06/13/345850
- o Clement K., Rees H., Canver, M. C., Gehrke J. M., F, Farouni, R., Hsu, J. Y., Cole, M., Liu D. R., Joung J. K., Bauer, D. E., Pinello, L. (2018). CRISPResso2: Characterization of repair outcomes and allele specific analysis from CRISPR nuclease and base editor genome editing.(submitted).

Preprints

Farouni, R. (2017). A Contemporary Overview of Probabilistic Latent Variable Models. arXiv preprint. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08137

Dissertation and Thesis

- o Farouni, R. (2017). Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States. *PhD Dissertation*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1492189894812539&disposition=inline
- o Farouni, R. (2014). Latent Variable Models of Categorical Responses in the Bayesian and Frequentist Frameworks. *Masters Thesis*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1412374136&disposition=inline

Conference Presentations

Joint Statistical Meetings

Seattle

Poster Presentation

2015

Poster Title: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model (available at https://rfarouni.github.io/assets/posters/jsm2015.pdf).

Journal Review Service.....

Psychometrika

Ad Hoc Reviewer

2015

Psychological Methods

Ad Hoc Reviewer

2016

Software Development

- o Haystack: A Python bioinformatics pipeline for the identification of genomic regions of epigenetic variability across different cell-types, cell-type specific cis-regulatory elements, and their associated transcription factors. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/pinellolab/haystack_bio.
- o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE.

Awards and Fellowships

0	Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award The Ohio State University	2015
0	The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship The Ohio State University	2015
	Project Proposal : 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'	
0	The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship The Ohio State University	2014
0	University Fellowship The Ohio State University	2012

Technical Skill Set

- Statistics and Machine Learning
 - **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R*, *Python* depending on computing goals. Familiar with *Julia*.
 - Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Tensorflow and Keras.
 - Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan, familiar with Edward.
- o **Bioinformatics Software:** Analysis of next generation sequencing data, R's Bioconductor core packages, Bowtie2, bedtools.
- **Cluster and High-Performance Computing:** Good knowledge of running bioinformatics analysis pipelines on super-computing clusters.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

Personal Details

- o Country of Current Residence: Canada
- o Countries of Previous Residence: USA, Russia, Jordan
- o Marital Status: Married
- o Interests and Hobbies: Theoretical Linguistics, Evolutionary Biology, Experimental Music
- Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (intermediate), French (elementary)